<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abstracts | David Sinden</title>
    <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://djps.github.io/abstracts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Abstracts</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://djps.github.io/media/logo_hu1617270246782058896.png</url>
      <title>Abstracts</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrability, localisation and bifurcation of an elastic conducting rod in a uniform magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/hamburg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/hamburg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the problem of electrodynamic space tethers, the equilibrium equations for an elastic conducting rod in a magnetic field are investigated. In body coordinates the equations are found to sit in a family of noncanonical Hamiltonian systems. These systems, which include the classical Euler and Kirchhoff rods, are shown to be completely integrable under certain material conditions. Mel’nikov method is then used to show that two integrable perturbations can in fact destroy the integrable structure, resulting in multimodal rod configurations. Such solutions are investigated numerically revealing a rich bifurcation structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
# bamc
We consider the equilibrium equations of a conducting rod in a uniform magnetic field, motivated by the problem of elctrodynamic tethers. The equations sit in a hierarchy of non-canonical Hamiltonian systems and are integrable if the rod is transversely isotropic, giving a physical realisation to a previously proposed abstract system. The integrals are used to reduce the problem to a four-dimensional canonical system, allowing the geometry of the phase space to be investigated through Poincare sections. When the rod is initially aligned with the magnetic field the system is superintegrable: the phase space breaks down into periodic orbits, corresponding to helical configurations of the rod. --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence in Therapeutic Ultrasound</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/lyon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/lyon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This educational talk presents an accessible introduction to the basic methods and terminology in artificial intelligence which could be applied to develop tools for therapeutic ultrasound delivery. The talk begins with an introduction to AI, focusing on what different neural networks are, and what is necessary to train a network. With this knowledge, a small number of applications are presented, covering segmentation and registration, treatment planning and physics-informed neural networks, treatment monitoring and outcome prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient-Specific Modelling of Microwave Ablation</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/stm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/stm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;: For the frequencies used in radiofrequency ablation it is possible to simplify the harmonic Maxwell equations by considering a quasi-static approximation. The problem reduces to a generalised Laplace equation, which can be solved in a straight forward manner. However, for the frequencies used in microwave ablation, the assumptions which lead to this model are longer valid. Solving the time-harmonic Maxwell equations can be computationally demanding. In order to overcome this, many predictions regarding ablation volumes in needle-based microwave ablation use ellipsoids which are derived from axisymmetric finite-element models, validated against homogeneous phantom data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, patient data is not homogeneous, and the presence of vascular structures or tumour heterogeneity mean that predicted ablation volumes based on axisymmetric models may not be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: We present a numerical scheme, based on a finite-difference frequency-domain scheme, which can model the electromagnetic, thermal and dosimetric fields for continuous wave exposures on patient data. Data from segmented DICOM images is used to form a number of staggered-grids. A perfectly matched layer suppresses spurious numerical artefacts from the boundary of the domain. A novel preconditioner is constructed which significantly accelerates the computation of the electro-magnetic field. The input into the simulation is provided as the electro-magnetic field in a homogeneous medium. This can be obtained via measurements or via an analytical model, for example by modelling the probe as a dipole source in a vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;: The advantage is that the scheme is fully three-dimensional, can be simulated in inhomogeneous media on large, clinically relevant, domains and can simulate multiple exposures. Having computed the electro-magnetic field for a set of material properties, strategies are presented to update electro-magnetic field as the material properties change due to temperature, dehydration or coagulation in order to reduce the duration of simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Validation is performed by comparing the predicted and measured ablated volumes, while considering the sources of uncertainty for both the numerical model, such as staircasing errors, and the experimental results, such as in the identification of the ablated regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;: A numerical scheme is presented which may allow patient-specific treatment planning to be performed for microwave ablation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factors for validation of measurement-based simulation</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/asa_virtual/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/asa_virtual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In many instances of therapeutic ultrasound it is preferable to produce near-field measurement-based simulations, rather than perform direct measurements. For example simulation from near-field measurements may have lower uncertainties than direct measurements at higher pressures; the entire field can be inspected and differing material properties can be modelled rather than make repeated measurements. However, to properly validate an approach there needs to be an understanding of uncertainties in data acquisition, the limitations of the governing equations and errors from the numerical methods employed. These are not independent, and are primarily determined by a combination of three factors: duration, intensity and inhomogeneity. Criteria for characterizing each factor are presented and consequent procedures outlined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements should consider burst length, positioning from transducer, spatial spacing, required resolution and averaging. From measurements, phase unwrapping and interpolation methods, pseudo-continuous wave approximations, as well as sparse and low-rank methods for data completion or identification of outliers, can be used to characterized the transducer as an initial source condition in an appropriate governing equation. This should consider transmission losses and reflections, frequency-dependent attenuation relations, shock-capturing and -fitting schemes, absorbing boundary conditions and the characterization of source terms for thermal simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing generalized multi-pool exchange tissue model MRI simulations for the modelling of an ultra-low field scanner</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/ismrm_virtual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/ismrm_virtual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The abstract can be found on the ISMRM website &lt;a href=&#34;https://cds.ismrm.org/protected/20MProceedings/PDFfiles/3655.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poster can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/posters/ISMRM2020.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Proc. Intl. Soc. Mag. Reson. Med. 28 (2020) Abstract &amp;#35;3655 --&gt;
&lt;!-- Assessing generalized multi-pool exchange tissue model MRI simulations for the modelling of an ultra-low field scanner
Ignacio Xavier Partarrieu1, Elliot Fox1,2, Frederic Brochu1, Matt Cashmore1, Neha Koonjoo3, Sheng Shen3, David Sinden1, Matthew Rosen3, and Matt G. Hall1,4
1National Physical Laboratory, Teddington, United Kingdom, 2Durham University, Durham, United Kingdom, 3Harvard, Boston, MA, United States, 4University College London, London, United Kingdom
--&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;synopsis&#34;&gt;Synopsis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The large expense and running costs of traditional 1.5T scanners have meant that as demand for scans has grown supply has not been able to keep up. Novel, ultra-low field systems aim to address this problem by producing images with some resolution losses as a trade-off for reduced costs. However, access to such devices is currently restricted, limiting the possible research output. In this work we develop and test a simulation model of 6.5 mT b-SSFP acquisitions, which we compare to actual scanner acquisitions. We find that such simulations produce qualitatively and quantitatively similar images to real scans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a newly emergent interest in ultra-low field (ULF) MRI, driven by recent successes in the field and cost-cutting pressures in healthcare. In particular, scanners with a cost of less than $50,000 have been reported &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which is within the reach of consortia of general practitioners. This means that such devices could potentially be used as a decision tool for the triage of patients, identifying those which might need higher resolution scans and those for which no follow-up is necessary. This would reduce some of the throughput pressures currently faced by hospitals. Simulations of ULF MRI scanners would be useful in helping to determine whether they can provide the information necessary for this and permit multiple researchers to carry out research at once, without needing access to the highly specialized equipment. In this work we have developed and tested software for creating such simulations and found them to be representative of ultra-low field acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ULF scanner described by Sarracanie &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; was chosen as the basis of this simulation, which was implemented using MRiLab &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The b-SSFP sequence described within was replicated by adapting the FIESTA sequence within the software to have a TR of 22.5 ms as described in the paper, with a voxel size of 2.5×3.5×11.5 mm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; . The MRiLab GUI was bypassed, with changes made directly to the gradient codes to avoid some undesired default assumptions, such as identical rise times for all pulses within a gradient sequence. Additionally, the ULF scanner uses a bespoke wound Litz coil to improve signal. This atypical coil presents several advantages in the ULF environment and was modelled by coding in an Archimedean spiral coil element for MRiLab. The ULF k-space acquisition scheme, with Gaussian sampling of half of the k-space, zero padded to be a 96×96 matrix, was also simulated, though the Gaussian sampling was applied post-simulation. The reconstructed simulation image was filtered using anisotropic diffusion through the Perona-Malik filter as implemented in MATLAB, with a gradient threshold of 10% and only two iterations. The change of spin values at ULF was also considered, and values were adjusted using extrapolation based on historical MR data &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, though it is unsure that these rules hold at ultra-low fields, as there are limited reports of T1 and T2 measurements at this field strength. An acquisition of a resolution phantom on the ULF MRI scanner was used for qualitative and quantitative comparison. The latter was performed using the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), defined as mean over the phantom area vs. standard deviation of the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A slice of the ULF acquisition of the resolution phantom may be seen in &lt;a href=&#34;#fig1&#34;&gt;figure 1&lt;/a&gt;, and a slice of the simulated brain phantom is shown in &lt;a href=&#34;#fig2&#34;&gt;figure 2&lt;/a&gt;. Qualitative inspection of these shows similar intensity and noise properties, though some of the finer structures normally visible in the brain phantom have been blurred. The SNR of the brain phantom is 21.9, which is slightly higher than the value calculated for the resolution phantom, which is 19.2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;width:50%; display:table-cell;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://djps.github.io/img/ISMRM2020-004304_Fig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Acquisition of phantom&#34;&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;fig1&#34;&gt;Figure 1&lt;/a&gt;: b-SSFP acquisition of a resolution phantom on a 6.5 mT scanner&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;width:50%; display:table-cell;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://djps.github.io/img/ISMRM2020-004304_Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Acquisition of phantom&#34;&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;fig2&#34;&gt;Figure 2&lt;/a&gt;: Simulated 6.5 mT b-SSFP acquisition of the brain phantom&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion&#34;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MRiLab is capable of simulating ULF MRI acquisitions accurately, though care is required to ensure that physical parameters such as T1, T2 and T2* are still representative. Though visual inspection and SNR values suggest that the simulation is accurate, further validation is needed by simulating and measuring known quantitative objects or simulating and measuring the same standard object. The slight difference in SNR could be due to either a lower noise contribution in the simulation than could be expected, or differences in the implementation of the filtering process such as in the gradient threshold or the number of iterations. A next step in the validation of the model would be to use simulations and acquisitions of the same known object to investigate both SNR and contrast-to-noise metrics, in order to ensure that the information content is similar and that the simulations do not lose or gain contrast from discretisation effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulations using MRiLab appear to provide value even for ultra-low field investigations. This can be used for the testing of hypotheses in less time and more cheaply than for physical investigations and provide access to ULF testing to researchers without their own ULF scanner. Further validation work involving the simulation of various objects will provide more detail on the limitations and advantages of this method of investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was funded by CRUK grant C69862/A29020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M. Sarracanie, C. LaPierre, N. Salameh et al. Low-Cost High-Performance MRI. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/srep15177&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;, 15177 (2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F. Liu, J. V. Velikina, W. F. Block, R. Kijowski &amp;amp; A. A. Samsonov, Fast Realistic MRI Simulations Based on Generalized Multi-Pool Exchange Tissue Model. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/TMI.2016.2620961&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;IEEE Trans. Med. Imaging&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;36&lt;/strong&gt;, 527–537 (2017).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. D. Rooney et al. Magnetic field and tissue dependencies of human brain longitudinal &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O relaxation in vivo. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1002/mrm.21122&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Magn. Reson. Med.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;57&lt;/strong&gt;, 308–318 (2007).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcostal High-Intensity Focused Ultrasound: Planning Treatment Delivery for Phased Arrays</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/vegas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/vegas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this presentation we describe a comprehensive package of computation procedures developed for treatment planning and treatment delivery for transcostal high-intensity focused ultrasound using a phased-array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of robust computational routines designed to identify a target area, specify the position of the transducer, then perform parallelised ray-tracing from segmented CT data to ascertain the optimal position and angulation has been developed.  The aim is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimize transmission losses through the skin/water interface arising from the angle of incidence between the field from each active element and the skin interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimize the propagation path in tissue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize the number of available elements which may be switched on if a isobaric beam corresponding to a given pressure value does not pass through the ribs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that the transducer can be viewed by an optical tracking system, in order to register the position of the treatment head to the position defined by the treatment plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that an imaging probe located in the central aperture of the treatment head can image the target, for treatment monitoring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that organs at risk such as lungs or bowel are not exposed to the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The location of an optical tracker placed on the transducer head is calculated, so that the location of the treatment head location compared to the treatment plan can be verified. For ease of identifying the location of ablated regions, surface lesions can be generated automatically. From the computed position image planes which can be compared with ultrasound images are computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appropriate phases can be calculated so that the acoustic intensity on the ribs is constrained using a boundary element method.  A Rayleigh integral method, is used where the acoustic window is sufficiently large, or the tolerances of the ray-tracing algorithm sufficiently strict . For a given exposure duration, the amplitudes of each element required to give either a user-defined focal peak temperature rise or a volumetric dose as a function of the full-width half maximum are calculated. Thermal calculations are performed using a parallelised alternating-direction implicit method on a structured rectilinear grid derived from the unstructured polydata sets of the surface meshes of the skin, ribs and liver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algorithms for motion compensation are introduced in order that motion can be exploited to enlarge the volume of the lesions treated, while still delivering a specified dose to the enlarged planning treatment volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computation routines are written in python and fortran, with bindings performed with &lt;a href=&#34;https://numpy.org/doc/stable/f2py/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;f2py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, graphical user interface from &lt;code&gt;wxpython&lt;/code&gt; and three-dimensional visualisation using &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.enthought.com/mayavi/mayavi/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mayavi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;mkl&lt;/code&gt; libraries are used extensively. Patient data can be provided as DICOM images for target identification, while registered and segmented anatomical data can be provided as an &lt;code&gt;.stl&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.vtk&lt;/code&gt; dataset. Settings are outputted as &lt;code&gt;.xml&lt;/code&gt; data in &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; files for ease in a human readable format, as well as text files which can be passed directly to a phased-array drive system. The system has been designed and implemented on an in-house high-performance computing facility, and is designed to be flexible for a variety of transducer designs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A comparison between theory and experiment in thermal ablation of perfused livers</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/npl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/npl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Authors: D. Sinden, V. Bull, J. Civale, I. Rivens, D. Holroyd &amp; G. ter Haar --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a vast literature on heat deposition by high-intensity focused ultrasound, much of the work tends to focus on a single approach. This talk provides a unified analysis of the heating due to HIFU, combing experimental, analytical and numerical approaches. One of the aims of this study is to ascertain the validity of the governing equations using clinically relevant experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six freshly excised porcine livers were repeatedly exposed to five seconds of continuous high-intensity focused ultrasound at 1.7 MHz by a single element transducer at a variety of intensities, in a variety of locations beneath the surface of the liver, while being perfused an by a OrganOx Metra, an prototype adaptive-perfusion system.  Using ultrasound imaging to identify significant objects around the focal region, exposures were either performed at as distance close as possible to a thermally significant vessel and at a distance of approximately 0.5 cm from the vessel wall. The measured vessel diameter was 4 mm and the flow within the vessel was measured using Doppler ultrasound to be approximately 9 cm/s. A fibre-optic hydrophone measured the acoustic and thermal fields at the focus, sampling at a rate of 200 Hz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a single element, unsteered transducer the Khokhlov-Zabolotskaya-Kuznetsov (KZK) equation, modelling nonlinear wave propagation through both water and soft-tissue, was coupled to the bioheat transfer equation, from which the thermal-dose is calculated. Using the range of values from tissue characterisation measurements, distributions were found which matched the spread of data for various acoustic and thermal properties. Hence empirically derived confidence intervals for various material parameters were formulated. A sensitivity analysis was performed on the governing equations to show the relative importance of each of the acoustic and thermal properties. Simulations are found to be in good agreement with experimental data away from the vessels within the range of uncertainties of tissue properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results from numerical and experiment data are presented, compared and discussed in the context of the implications for therapeutic ultrasound treatment planning, specifically for the effects of cavitation enhanced heating and the viability of treatment next to thermally significant large vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
