<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | djps</title>
    <link>https://djps.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://djps.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://djps.github.io/media/logo_hud7cfbe45e4df55bd5c7c181ea654d8f2_56982_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>QualiPerF</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/project/qualiperf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/project/qualiperf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;quantifying-liver-perfusion-function-relationship-in-complex-resection--a-systems-medicine-approach&#34;&gt;Quantifying Liver Perfusion-Function Relationship in Complex Resection – A Systems Medicine Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of the research unit is to better predict the recovery of hepatic function during regeneration after liver surgery of diseased livers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hepatic disease affect hepatic processes at different spatial scales: individual hepatocytes, hepatic sinusoids/lobuli (including zonated phenomena), the organ, and the entire organism. Surgery and subsequent regeneration further perturb the hepatic processes at the different scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In QuaLiPerF, these effects will be included in computational models of the metabolization of selected test compounds representative for liver function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to build a multi-scale computational model of test compound metabolism during liver regeneration. For this purpose, this project will integrate models at the cellular, lobular, and organism scale (by the modeling partners) with own models at the organ scale, in a four- scale framework. Combining the relevant complex and interacting processes in a computational model will require a deep understanding of the underlying physiology, biology, and biochemistry and of suitable modeling techniques for the respective spatial scales. Our mechanistically driven model translation and integration will be complemented by a data-driven approach in collaboration with the data integration partner. The computational models to be developed will be parameterized and validated using clinical and experimental physiological and metabolic data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, this project will combine the data acquired during regeneration to descriptive computational model of the recovery of physiological and metabolic parameters over time, to be combined with the models of test compound metabolization. Predictions obtained from simulations using the computational models will be used in QuaLiPerF to investigate biological and clinical questions driven by the clinical and experimental partners. Ultimately, a better prediction of the recovery of liver function developed in QuaLiPerF will help improve planning of individual surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EHMA</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/project/ehma/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/project/ehma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;enhancing-hepatic-microwave-ablation&#34;&gt;Enhancing Hepatic Microwave Ablation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CUBDL: Challenge on Ultrasound Beamforming with Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/project/cubdl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/project/cubdl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge-on-ultrasound-beamforming-with-deep-learning&#34;&gt;Challenge on Ultrasound Beamforming with Deep Learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details can be found at the organisers website &lt;a href=&#34;https://cubdl.jhu.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Award is &lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/uploads/Challenge-mevis-team.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cosserat Theory</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/project/cosserat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/project/cosserat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;deformation-of-an-elastic-rod-in-a-magnetic-field&#34;&gt;Deformation of an elastic rod in a magnetic field&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my PhD which was undertaken at &lt;a href=&#34;https://ucl.ac.uk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UCL&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/civil-environmental-geomatic-engineering/people/prof-gert-van-der-heijden&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Gert van der Heijden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thesis can be found online &lt;a href=&#34;https://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/id/eprint/15832/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/publication/thesis&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journal publications can be found&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/publication/sinden2008ice&#34;&gt;Integrability of a conducting elastic rod in a magnetic field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/publication/sinden2008sce&#34;&gt;Spatial chaos of an extensible conducting rod in a uniform magnetic field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conference proceeding can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/publication/sinden2011bmc&#34;&gt;The Buckling of Magneto-Strictive Cosserat Rods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://djps.github.io/publication/vanderheijden2011ltc&#34;&gt;Localisation of a twisted conducting rod in a uniform magnetic field: the Hamiltonian-Hopf-Hopf bifurcation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
