<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thermal Ablation | David Sinden</title>
    <link>https://djps.github.io/tag/thermal-ablation/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://djps.github.io/tag/thermal-ablation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Thermal Ablation</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://djps.github.io/media/logo_hud7cfbe45e4df55bd5c7c181ea654d8f2_56982_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Thermal Ablation</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/tag/thermal-ablation/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>EHMA</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/project/ehma/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/project/ehma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;enhancing-hepatic-microwave-ablation&#34;&gt;Enhancing Hepatic Microwave Ablation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- https://gepris.dfg.de/gepris/projekt/261433767?language=en --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Studying the effect of tissue properties on radiofrequency ablation by visual simulation ensemble analysis</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/publication/heimes2022set/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/publication/heimes2022set/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Meeting of the Society for Thermal Medicine 2022</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/post/stm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/post/stm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Presentation at virtual conference on solving the curl-curl form of Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations for needle-based microwave ablations based on segmented patient data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference site, with details on talks and schedules, can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://virtual.oxfordabstracts.com/#/event/2827/program&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference homepage can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thermaltherapy.org/ebusSFTM/ANNUALMEETING/2022AnnualMeeting.aspx&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation can be accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/14iCxWJDalBKcaAig3bISRLaq8vt7-Fn7/view&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;patient-specific-modelling-of-microwave-ablation&#34;&gt;Patient-Specific Modelling of Microwave Ablation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;: For the frequencies used in radiofrequency ablation it is possible to simplify the harmonic Maxwell equations by considering a quasi-static approximation. The problem reduces to a generalised Laplace equation, which can be solved in a straight forward manner. However, for the frequencies used in microwave ablation, the assumptions which lead to this model are longer valid. Solving the time-harmonic Maxwell equations can be computationally demanding. In order to overcome this, many predictions regarding ablation volumes in needle-based microwave ablation use ellipsoids which are derived from axisymmetric finite-element models, validated against homogeneous phantom data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, patient data is not homogeneous, and the presence of vascular structures or tumour heterogeneity mean that predicted ablation volumes based on axisymmetric models may not be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: We present a numerical scheme, based on a finite-difference frequency-domain scheme, which can model the electromagnetic, thermal and dosimetric fields for continuous wave exposures on patient data. Data from segmented DICOM images is used to form a number of staggered-grids. A perfectly matched layer suppresses spurious numerical artefacts from the boundary of the domain. A novel preconditioner is constructed which significantly accelerates the computation of the electro-magnetic field. The input into the simulation is provided as the electro-magnetic field in a homogeneous medium. This can be obtained via measurements or via an analytical model, for example by modelling the probe as a dipole source in a vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;: The advantage is that the scheme is fully three-dimensional, can be simulated in inhomogeneous media on large, clinically relevant, domains and can simulate multiple exposures. Having computed the electro-magnetic field for a set of material properties, strategies are presented to update electro-magnetic field as the material properties change due to temperature, dehydration or coagulation in order to reduce the duration of simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Validation is performed by comparing the predicted and measured ablated volumes, while considering the sources of uncertainty for both the numerical model, such as staircasing errors, and the experimental results, such as in the identification of the ablated regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;: A numerical scheme is presented which may allow patient-specific treatment planning to be performed for microwave ablation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient-Specific Modelling of Microwave Ablation</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/stm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/stm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;: For the frequencies used in radiofrequency ablation it is possible to simplify the harmonic Maxwell equations by considering a quasi-static approximation. The problem reduces to a generalised Laplace equation, which can be solved in a straight forward manner. However, for the frequencies used in microwave ablation, the assumptions which lead to this model are longer valid. Solving the time-harmonic Maxwell equations can be computationally demanding. In order to overcome this, many predictions regarding ablation volumes in needle-based microwave ablation use ellipsoids which are derived from axisymmetric finite-element models, validated against homogeneous phantom data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, patient data is not homogeneous, and the presence of vascular structures or tumour heterogeneity mean that predicted ablation volumes based on axisymmetric models may not be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: We present a numerical scheme, based on a finite-difference frequency-domain scheme, which can model the electromagnetic, thermal and dosimetric fields for continuous wave exposures on patient data. Data from segmented DICOM images is used to form a number of staggered-grids. A perfectly matched layer suppresses spurious numerical artefacts from the boundary of the domain. A novel preconditioner is constructed which significantly accelerates the computation of the electro-magnetic field. The input into the simulation is provided as the electro-magnetic field in a homogeneous medium. This can be obtained via measurements or via an analytical model, for example by modelling the probe as a dipole source in a vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;: The advantage is that the scheme is fully three-dimensional, can be simulated in inhomogeneous media on large, clinically relevant, domains and can simulate multiple exposures. Having computed the electro-magnetic field for a set of material properties, strategies are presented to update electro-magnetic field as the material properties change due to temperature, dehydration or coagulation in order to reduce the duration of simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Validation is performed by comparing the predicted and measured ablated volumes, while considering the sources of uncertainty for both the numerical model, such as staircasing errors, and the experimental results, such as in the identification of the ablated regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;: A numerical scheme is presented which may allow patient-specific treatment planning to be performed for microwave ablation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcostal High-Intensity Focused Ultrasound: Planning Treatment Delivery for Phased Arrays</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/vegas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/vegas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this presentation we describe a comprehensive package of computation procedures developed for treatment planning and treatment delivery for transcostal high-intensity focused ultrasound using a phased-array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of robust computational routines designed to identify a target area, specify the position of the transducer, then perform parallelised ray-tracing from segmented CT data to ascertain the optimal position and angulation has been developed.  The aim is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimize transmission losses through the skin/water interface arising from the angle of incidence between the field from each active element and the skin interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimize the propagation path in tissue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximize the number of available elements which may be switched on if a isobaric beam corresponding to a given pressure value does not pass through the ribs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that the transducer can be viewed by an optical tracking system, in order to register the position of the treatment head to the position defined by the treatment plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that an imaging probe located in the central aperture of the treatment head can image the target, for treatment monitoring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that organs at risk such as lungs or bowel are not exposed to the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The location of an optical tracker placed on the transducer head is calculated, so that the location of the treatment head location compared to the treatment plan can be verified. For ease of identifying the location of ablated regions, surface lesions can be generated automatically. From the computed position image planes which can be compared with ultrasound images are computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appropriate phases can be calculated so that the acoustic intensity on the ribs is constrained using a boundary element method.  A Rayleigh integral method, is used where the acoustic window is sufficiently large, or the tolerances of the ray-tracing algorithm sufficiently strict . For a given exposure duration, the amplitudes of each element required to give either a user-defined focal peak temperature rise or a volumetric dose as a function of the full-width half maximum are calculated. Thermal calculations are performed using a parallelised alternating-direction implicit method on a structured rectilinear grid derived from the unstructured polydata sets of the surface meshes of the skin, ribs and liver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algorithms for motion compensation are introduced in order that motion can be exploited to enlarge the volume of the lesions treated, while still delivering a specified dose to the enlarged planning treatment volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computation routines are written in python and fortran, with bindings performed with &lt;a href=&#34;https://numpy.org/doc/stable/f2py/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;f2py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, graphical user interface from &lt;code&gt;wxpython&lt;/code&gt; and three-dimensional visualisation using &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.enthought.com/mayavi/mayavi/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mayavi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;mkl&lt;/code&gt; libraries are used extensively. Patient data can be provided as DICOM images for target identification, while registered and segmented anatomical data can be provided as an &lt;code&gt;.stl&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.vtk&lt;/code&gt; dataset. Settings are outputted as &lt;code&gt;.xml&lt;/code&gt; data in &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; files for ease in a human readable format, as well as text files which can be passed directly to a phased-array drive system. The system has been designed and implemented on an in-house high-performance computing facility, and is designed to be flexible for a variety of transducer designs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A comparison between theory and experiment in thermal ablation of perfused livers</title>
      <link>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/npl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://djps.github.io/abstracts/npl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Authors: D. Sinden, V. Bull, J. Civale, I. Rivens, D. Holroyd &amp; G. ter Haar --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a vast literature on heat deposition by high-intensity focused ultrasound, much of the work tends to focus on a single approach. This talk provides a unified analysis of the heating due to HIFU, combing experimental, analytical and numerical approaches. One of the aims of this study is to ascertain the validity of the governing equations using clinically relevant experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six freshly excised porcine livers were repeatedly exposed to five seconds of continuous high-intensity focused ultrasound at 1.7 MHz by a single element transducer at a variety of intensities, in a variety of locations beneath the surface of the liver, while being perfused an by a OrganOx Metra, an prototype adaptive-perfusion system.  Using ultrasound imaging to identify significant objects around the focal region, exposures were either performed at as distance close as possible to a thermally significant vessel and at a distance of approximately 0.5 cm from the vessel wall. The measured vessel diameter was 4 mm and the flow within the vessel was measured using Doppler ultrasound to be approximately 9 cm/s. A fibre-optic hydrophone measured the acoustic and thermal fields at the focus, sampling at a rate of 200 Hz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a single element, unsteered transducer the Khokhlov-Zabolotskaya-Kuznetsov (KZK) equation, modelling nonlinear wave propagation through both water and soft-tissue, was coupled to the bioheat transfer equation, from which the thermal-dose is calculated. Using the range of values from tissue characterisation measurements, distributions were found which matched the spread of data for various acoustic and thermal properties. Hence empirically derived confidence intervals for various material parameters were formulated. A sensitivity analysis was performed on the governing equations to show the relative importance of each of the acoustic and thermal properties. Simulations are found to be in good agreement with experimental data away from the vessels within the range of uncertainties of tissue properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results from numerical and experiment data are presented, compared and discussed in the context of the implications for therapeutic ultrasound treatment planning, specifically for the effects of cavitation enhanced heating and the viability of treatment next to thermally significant large vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
